The science and practice of enhancing
human performance for sport, play, and
life.
Welcome to Perform.
I'm Andy Galpin, and I'm the executive
director of the Human Performance Center
at Parker University. Today, we're going
to be talking all about how to develop a
strong core and great-looking abs. And I
figured we'd get started with a bit of a
warm-up to get your brain going, and
I'll ask some simple questions that all
of you definitely know the right answer
to.
Let's get started with some basics.
If I picked a couple of different
exercises, could you tell me which ones
are better for developing your core and
abs, and which one is least effective?
Let's throw out some simple ones.
What about a sit-up versus a deadlift?
I'm sure most of you are thinking, "Of
course, it's a sit-up." But are you
really sure? What about if we did
something like a machine versus a free
weight exercise?
Do we automatically know
that the machine will activate my core
less,
and the free weights will do more, and
therefore be better for my ab
development than the machine?
I know what you're thinking. Oh, well,
when I have my free weights, I've got to
create stability, and I've got to
regulate it. That's got to be activating
my core more.
But is it really?
What does the science really say
about machines versus free weights?
How often do we train our core?
Oh, every day. They're small muscles.
They recover.
Are you sure that that's how it works?
And so, when actually preparing for this
episode, I started to realize there's so
many topics like this in how people are
generally training their abs and their
core that are not actually in line with
the current scientific evidence.
Which is funny, because if we were to
ask all of you, I'm basically every
human being would like a strong core and
great-looking abs. So, we all want it,
but as the saying goes, you'll find more
people that have a million dollars in
the bank account than those that have a
six-pack. Here's the good story, though.
We actually can solve this problem
pretty easily. We'll have to start off
by actually understanding the difference
between the core and abs.
We also need to take into account what
outcome I'm really looking for. And once
we understand that, we'll actually
understand how some of these questions
are answered differently
based upon my goal.
So, in today's episode, I would love to
walk you through exactly that.
What is the core? How do our abs
actually work? That will then give us
insights into how we should train based
upon our unique goals and demands. And
spoiler alert there,
we don't all mean the same thing when we
say we want a strong core and great abs.
What variables do I manipulate? What
exercises do I choose? What order do I
do them in? How frequently? How heavy?
What repetition range? All of these
questions and more are going to be
answered here in today's episode. And
so, my hope is you will leave this with
all of your questions answered, having a
better guide and understanding for
developing your core and your abs for
whatever goal you choose.
The presenting sponsor of this podcast
is Momentous. Momentous makes the
highest quality supplements on the
market, period. I literally spent years
vetting their products, company, and
leadership team before officially
partnering with them in 2023. Every
single one of Momentous's products is
third-party tested to ensure quality,
and many are even NSF certified for
sport. Now, while I love all their
products, I'm incredibly excited about
their new Fiber Plus Prebiotic.
Almost everyone is seeking more energy,
improved recovery, and better
performance. But most people are missing
a key foundation to their overall
health, and that's getting enough good
fiber. In fact, 95% of Americans are
failing to hit the recommended daily
amount of fiber. Fiber powers gut
health, which we know drives long-term
performance. Proper gut health allows
for better nutrient absorption, energy
stability, recovery, inflammation
control, and much more. I personally
simply mix a scoop with our cinnamon
flavor and some water every night, and
by doing so, I make sure I'm covering
any gaps I might have in my daily fiber
intake that I try to get through eating
a balanced whole food diet. If you'd
like to try Fiber Plus or any of
Momentous's best-in-class supplements,
just go to livemomentous.com/galpin
and use the code galpin for up to 35%
off your first order. Again, that's
livemomentous.com/galpin
and use the code galpin for up to 35%
off your first order.
If you're anything like me, you've
probably gone through a phase of your
life where you've done all of the
sit-ups and crunches you could possibly
do, you've hit all the planks,
and you still not gotten many results.
But I want to get started with how we
got here in the first place.
Why is it people take their abdominals
and their core and train them with the
endless crunches and sit-ups, with the
planks? Now, the reason most people
train their abs this way actually comes
from a good place.
If you go back to the 1960s and '70s,
these legendary figures in fitness and
strength and conditioning, like Joe
Weider and Arnold Schwarzenegger, were
big proponents of training a lot of
repetitions. So, tons of sets, tons of
reps per set, many days per week. In
fact, this is exactly how Arnold
outlined it in his legendary
encyclopedia training book. And so, we
started from that place. Now, not all
bodybuilders at the time subscribed to
that. Some did it differently. But
Arnold was if one of if not the most
famous person in the field ever, and so
that really carried it into the
mainstream. You roll into the 1980s, and
you have now the explosion of Pilates
and Jane Fonda and literally the
8-minute ab workouts. And these are all
focused on burn, burn, burn, burn, burn.
Right? Get your abs burning, and the
assumption is the more they burn, the
stronger they get. And while that's
reasonably okay to think, it's not as
precise and specific as it can be.
You had then the evolution of the 1990s
and early 2000s with people like Janda
and and McGill, who started taking the
abs more from the perspective of low
back pain,
and started saying, "Hey, your core is
important to your pain, and so we should
actually train it with the specific goal
of minimizing low back injury or pain."
People hadn't really done ab training
for this purpose before that. We didn't
really have discussions in the '70s,
'80s, '90s about why your back hurts,
why your hips hurt. It's because your
core is weak. And so, when we started to
unravel this stuff scientifically and
from the field, people had to start
saying, "Okay, well, you may be trained
like this if you want your abs to look
great, but maybe you train like that if
you just want your back to not hurt as
much." And this represents the first
bifurcation of this training approach.
And so, when you hear fitness
professionals,
physical therapists maybe differing from
your strength coaches in terms of how to
train your abs, it probably goes all the
way back to this initial changing point
where
what we're really talking about
is what is our outcome goal.
On one hand, you've got people who are
focused exclusively on making your abs
look a certain way,
and the others are coming at it from a
functionality perspective.
Now, I'm not here to tell you which one
is more important.
I am here to tell you, though, the
perspective in which they're educating
you will determine in large part what
they say works better
or worse.
That's the thing we're going to have to
keep in mind for the rest of this
episode. Our outcome goal
in large part determines what is better
or worse when it comes to training our
abs and our core. Now, before we go any
further, we need to actually discuss
what I mentioned a second ago, and that
is, what's the difference between your
abs and your core?
If I asked most of you out there, you'd
probably be like,
"I don't know. I thought they were the
same thing."
And of course, in large part they are,
but the precision matters right now,
because again, it will unveil insights
into how we best train them.
Generally, when we say things like your
abs, we're thinking aesthetics, you
know, how do you look rather than
function? Not always, but in general.
And we're generally talking about three
big groups of muscles. The first is
called your rectus abdominis. This is
the six-pack. This is right in the
middle.
The second are actually two muscle
groups combined, and that is your
obliques. These are the ones on your
side. And then the third is your
transverse abdominis.
I'll get into the anatomy in more detail
here in one moment, but keep this in
mind. So, generally, we think abs, we
think aesthetics, we think those three
groups of muscles.
When we go to the core, it is your abs
plus the whole host of other muscle
groups.
We're generally now talking about
performance
and outcome-based activities. So, it is
your abs, it's your pelvic floor, your
diaphragm, your rib cage. We actually
then go into your back. We start talking
about the four big groups of spinal
erectors and the deep spine muscles and
the QL and lateral trunk and and all
these things. If you're like, "What are
those?" Don't worry about it. Or go look
them up. It's not critical that you know
that right now.
But what is critical to understand is
that is as effective or important to
your core as your rectus abdominis.
We also then have things like your hip
stabilizers, your glute muscles. In
fact, some people will look at the
muscles of the upper back and the
shoulder girdle and call those a part of
your core.
So, really, what we're saying is your
core is everything not your limbs, not
your forearm, not your knee, not your
toes.
And so, then it becomes really
complicated because there's
it's reasonable to understand that we
probably don't have the exact same
training principles for your upper trap
muscle as I have for your diaphragm.
And that's probably not the same as it
is for your rectus abdominis.
And so, right out the gates here, we
start to go, "Oh, okay. I understand
that now training my rectus abdominis to
make me look like a nice six-pack might
have some slightly different principles
than training my multifidus in my low
back." That distinction right there will
clear up a lot of misconceptions. Now,
by the same token, it's also important
to understand that training your abs is
not exclusively for the purposes of
visual appearance.
We have excellent research now at this
point that will indicate things like a
weak core will increase your likelihood
of things like low back pain.
So, it's not just something I do to look
better. We also have evidence from sport
performance, and admittedly this is a
little bit weaker.
You will not see a lot of research
directly translating, for example, how
many sit-ups you can do with how far you
can kick a soccer ball.
But, there is some stuff that provides
loose associations with general athletic
performance that says, "Hey,
if you have an insufficient core,
defined differently in every study,
that that probably leads to some slight
inefficiencies."
Most practitioners though were going to
tell you the eye test, from the
experience test, that if a core is weak,
you have a hard time transmitting force.
This is a fancy way of saying things
like, "If I am a rotational athlete, I
throw a baseball, I hit a golf ball, I
throw a javelin,
and I am able to transmit certain amount
of force through my hips and my feet
into the ground,
but then my core can't handle that
force, it may not translate into my arm
or my hand as much,
net resulting in me not hitting the ball
golf ball as far as I should or throwing
the javelin or baseball or what have
you."
And so, the framework I would like to
move forward with here is something I've
been using for a long time now, and that
is look, feel, and perform.
So, here's the outline.
When I talk about look, let's assume
this is people who are here primarily,
if not entirely, because they want their
abs to look better.
Again, as I just described, I don't have
any issue with that. Totally fine.
Everyone wants their abs to look better.
But, this is looking, right? It's often
times associated with things like
hypertrophy
and muscle growth there. So, we want
bigger, more defined abs, we want it to
look a certain way. The second category
is what I call feel.
And that is now more synonymous with
things like pain reduction. And so, I
don't want to feel in pain. I don't want
to feel weak. I don't want to feel
imbalanced.
And so, look number one, perform number
two is generally associated with
probably that low back pain type of
thing.
Third one is perform.
And this is easy to understand in terms
of I want to be more functional. I want
to hit, again, hit the golf ball harder.
I want to hit the baseball harder. I
want to be more feel more balanced when
I'm on my skateboard or my surfboard.
These are all expecting strengthening
your core to translate into more human
movement success. So, look, feel, and
perform. And what we're going to do
today is walk through how your training
should differ
depending on which of these goals
are most specific to you.
If you're listening to this and
thinking,
"I kind of want all that. I want my abs
to look better. I don't want to have any
back pain or I want my back pain to go
away, and I actually want my core to
feel stronger and actually be stronger."
Then I would actually say, "Great. Take
a little bit from each one of these
areas and apply them based on your
situation scenario, and you should walk
away with very practical,
specific examples of what to do, what to
not to do, and how to better set up your
training."
And so, here's where things get
confusing. If I took a a crunch exercise
or a sit-up, if you prefer that term,
and I asked a physical therapist
or asked a bodybuilding coach
or asked a personal trainer,
"What do you think about crunches?"
You might get three completely different
answers, and it could look something
like this.
Most are going to acknowledge the fact
that sit-ups and that type of flexion
activity
are going to activate, develop, and
engage the rectus abdominis. Remember,
that's your six-pack ab muscles in the
front.
But then the low back specialist
might look at this and go,
"Man, I hate crunches. I never use them.
They're the worst exercise ever because
it causes spinal flexion or load, and it
causes pain. Either it causes people to
develop back pain or those who have a
history of back pain, it might bring it
back or aggravate it even further, and
so on and so forth."
And they're not wrong.
But then you might go to the
bodybuilding coach who again says the
opposite, "I love it because
what we want in bodybuilding
to look like a strong core, we're
generally talking about the rectus
abdominis and not transverse and not
actually the obliques at all."
And then you're sitting there going
like, "Well, wait a minute. This world
champion bodybuilder told me they're
great, and then this
scientist, this excellent practitioner
told me they're terrible."
Well, they're both correct.
It's a matter of what we're going after,
why we're doing it, and what risks we're
willing to run. They're not wrong.
Different outcome goals, different
perspectives, different criteria.
So, this is the world that you're living
in, and I empathize with it, and that's
why I wanted to do this episode.
So, as we get into these different
goals, look, feel, and perform, let's
start walking through what exercises to
choose, the order to do them in, the
frequency, intensity, volume,
rest intervals, and then how to progress
these things over time, and we'll just
start by going through one by one.
So, with that understood, how do our
abdominal and core muscles actually
work?
>> [snorts]
>> As I mentioned,
anatomy-wise, there's the three big
groups, rectus abdominis, your internal
and external obliques are often times
smashed together and just called your
obliques, and your transverse abdominis,
and then you've got those other set of
core muscles.
Focusing on the rectus abdominis first,
you may be surprised to realize it's not
actually one muscle. In fact, if you've
ever seen that person that has their
shirt off and they either have 10,
and you're like, "That person doesn't
have a six-pack, they have a 10-pack."
Or they actually have a different
number.
Like I got four on one side and five on
another or they're completely offset.
That's actually because it's not one
muscle, it is more like a series of
little muscles with a load of connective
tissue that helps it transmit force.
So, the the rectus abdominis actually
starts just below your sternum, attaches
to the bottom of your rib cage on the
front side, and goes all the way down to
the front of your hip bone. And so, the
main activity of the rectus abdominis is
actually to pull your rib cage down.
So, when we get into things like a
sit-up exercise, sometimes people will
actually be sore or have pain in their
hip flexors when they do them.
That's generally because the rectus
abdominis again is supposed to move your
rib cage up. And so, if you're not
executing that exercise properly, and
you're you you're you're getting success
with flexion by moving your hips rather
than your ribs up,
then the hip flexors themselves and
things like the psoas major tend to get
sore or fatigued. It's also in large
part why people who get back pain from
this type of activity get it.
Often times they're doing the exercise
incorrectly, and they're using more of
the pelvis for the flexion portion
rather than the rectus abdominis itself.
So, that's that particular muscle. And
that's the one we think about when we
think of I want nice abs, we're almost
always looking at the RA muscle, that's
how we call it. The obliques themselves
are on the side. So, if you were to take
your hands and point them down to the
ground, so your fingers are pointing to
the ground, and you put them right on
your sides, so that your palm is on the
bottom of your ribs and your fingertips
are touching the top of your hips.
Those are your internal and external
obliques.
They are the side muscles. They are also
important for the aesthetics crowd cuz
that's what gives you that V shape or
that taper or helps kind of wrap the abs
around themselves to look a particular
way.
The transverse abdominis or the TVA is
the thing that helps us rotate from side
to side. It is our rotational movement.
Now, this right here causes controversy.
And I would actually shouldn't say
controversy, but misunderstanding.
Because the obliques are on the side,
and if you do any rotational movement,
you will know exactly what I'm talking
about.
You'll be ah, like sore on the sides.
The mistake here is the next muscle
group, right? That transverse abdominis.
The transverse abdominis is not the
muscle or groups of muscles that rotate
you in the transverse plane.
Do you see what happened there?
You'd think the transverse muscle is
what makes you transverse, rotates side
to side, but it is not. It's the
obliques. And so, because of that,
people do not train the transverse
appropriately because they're actually
confusing what it does. The transverse
abdominis is like a
giant weight belt around your entire
core. It goes from the bottom of your
ribs, from the front to the back, all
the way down to the bottom of your hip,
from the front to the back. It's like a
giant corset.
It's a huge thing that goes down,
connects the entire thing together.
Its primary function is to pull the
belly inward.
And so, when you've ever seen people
like yoga practitioners or jujitsu
fighters who can pull their stomach way
in and do the waves and control like
that, that is extreme control of the
transverse abdominis. That's not the
oblique muscles.
So, we want the ability to stabilize our
rib cage with our rectus abdominis. We
want to be able to rotate with our
obliques, and we want to be able to pull
the rib cage in
with our transverse abdominis. Anybody
with a lot of knowledge of anatomy will
actually tell you again, none of these
are individual muscles. They've got
dozens, I think the transverse abdominis
has like 28 individual muscles within
it. So, these are just big groups like
we kind of refer to your biceps. Your
biceps is not one muscle, it's biceps.
People forget the S on the end cuz
there's multiple, but you get the rough
point here.
Now, some people like to train and
approach the core based on muscle
groups.
Others do it by movement patterns. So,
those collective three groups of muscles
can make movement happen in several
different ways. And the first is what
I've already mentioned, that is flexion.
This is the sit-up. Okay, this is your
body coming closer together,
flexing forward. Then there's also
lateral flexion. This is a side bend,
right? This is you're reaching from one
side to the other where one oblique gets
stretched and one oblique gets crunched.
Both flexion, but now we have more
anterior flexion
and then now you have lateral flexion.
You also then have extension. This is
the opposite of flexion.
It's kind of a little wordy here, but
it's it's going backwards, right? This
is instead of bringing your chest closer
to your knees, it's doing the opposite
and bringing your back closer to your
hamstrings, like the extension portion.
And then you have rotation, of course,
moving side to side.
But around 25 years or so ago, people
like, but not exclusively, Dr. Stuart
McGill and plenty of others
were instrumental in saying, "Hey, look,
we're approaching this movement stuff
incorrectly."
Because remember,
prior to that, ab training was sit-ups
and crunches for Arnold and his friends.
And then maybe our Jane Fondas.
But what they started saying is really
the main driving function of our core
musculature is not movement.
It's stability.
And so like our biceps and our triceps
are there to move our elbow, to flex and
extend our elbow. That's their primary
job and most of our muscles.
The core is a little bit unique because
it is not meant to be a large flexor.
There's not a lot of human movement that
requires you to bring your rib cage to
your thighs.
It's mainly there to make you stable.
And so the easy analogy, I know some
people hate it, but I actually think it
works really well. If you were to take
your hand and place it flat on a table
and I want you to keep your hand and
spread your fingers as wide as you can.
And I want you to keep that entire
surface of your hand and your fingers
on that table as firm as you can.
And then I pulled your middle finger up
as high as I can.
And I pulled it up, pulled it up, pulled
it up, pulled it up and then I let it
go.
It'll snap to the ground.
Right? And if I do it again, it'll snap
to the ground.
Now, do the same thing, but I want you
to lift your hand off the table
so that that only the tips of your
fingers are still in contact with the
table.
And now I want you to pull your finger
up and snap it down.
It barely moves.
Not a perfect analogy here, but we're
trying to get to the concept that says,
"If your, in this case, the palm of your
hand
becomes unstable or is not stiff,
this does not allow
that appendage, in this case, the
finger,
to contract with a lot of power and
force.
The more stable,
the analogy here being your core is,
then the more force I can
transmit
And so the rationale here was saying,
"Wait a minute.
Again, not training only for aesthetics,
but training for performance or pain
mitigation and injury,
we need a stiff and stable core so that
our other appendages can move with more
force transmission and we're not putting
our spine at the same time in
dangerous positions."
Now, I want to be careful here. When I
say a stiff core, I don't mean rigid. I
don't want to be locked in and you can't
move. It just needs to be stiff and
strong when it's supposed to be strong
and pliable and motion and and movable
when it's supposed to be movement based.
So because of that, there was a
you know, earlier in my career, there
was this addition of core movements that
are anti-movements. And so you have your
flexion and now we needed to add in
anti-flexion exercises. We have rotation
and anti-rotation. We have extension and
anti-extension and lateral flexion and
anti-lateral flexion. And this was a
really big change.
And so we consistently saw, well, hey,
wait a minute here.
Different goals, different training
approaches. Aesthetics, again, we're
going to
in in large part, maybe focus a little
bit more on movement-based ab exercises.
For feel and perform,
maybe hedging a little bit more in the
anti-movement. So we've established this
idea of movement-based training and
anti-movement-based training.
But we still haven't really fully
understood why we default to doing a
style of training that is high
repetition,
high frequency.
Because none of our movement-based
approaches,
none of our other muscles get trained
that way.
So why did we get here and what can we
learn from that? Well, we also have to
understand,
the core is different, again, because it
does things like mostly avoid movement
rather than active movement. It's also
different because it's consistently
activated.
So your core muscles are usually at
about 2 to 3% of their maximum voluntary
contraction, which is like the most
force they can produce,
when you're standing.
And so again, unlike a tricep or a
bicep, your core is going at all times.
Not much, but it is going.
When you do basic activities like lift
up your backpack or grab a gallon of
water or something like that,
your core muscles get up to 30 to 40 to
50% of their force output right away.
Again, most of your other muscles
wouldn't get that high that quickly.
Your core will actually get up to
basically 100% during a sneeze.
In fact, this happens to me all the
time. It drives my wife nuts.
But I'm like vigorous sneezer. Like I
don't I'm not a baby sneezer. I go nuts
and I'll like core will get huge cramps
in it when I do it because I'm at a full
full full contraction. Uh this is the
same thing happens to me, sorry. This is
a little bit gross, but if I
It's like the most intense core
contraction I've ever had from top to
bottom.
And so your core has this ability to be
like slightly on, to go at really high
activation really fast, where other
muscles struggle for that.
So plant that in your back of your mind.
We have a muscle group or groups of
muscles that are
active a lot. They're one of your only
muscle groups that almost never turn
off. Most do.
Okay? We also have the understanding,
we've known this since like I think
there was a series of papers in in '96
and '97 that came out from
Paul Hodges
and Carolyn Richardson. And there was
this idea that's called fast forward
stabilization. So you may not realize
this, but your core will actually turn
on about 100 to 150 milliseconds
before your limbs will start movement.
It's an anticipatory response and it
goes right back to that finger and hand
analogy I just gave you.
In order for my finger, if if my finger
is an arm or leg, to snap and contract,
if that core isn't pre-activated, the
the arm itself can't do anything.
And so way before you will actually
acknowledge it when you have an
anticipation of a movement happening,
whether that's because you practice it a
lot or you've already pre-registered it
subconsciously, you'll have that early
activation of your core
before your movement.
So that is another thing. Okay, it's
activated early, it's on all the time,
it's being used for lots of different
things.
And then there's also this idea floating
around that
okay, muscles like your calves, muscles
like your abs that are slow twitch,
that are postural, that are on all the
time,
either need more training and or can
recover faster so you can train it more
frequently. This is the idea that you
should train your abs every day or your
calves every day or most days.
And it's based on rationale of what I
just said, as well as things like, "Oh,
maybe our core muscles are way more slow
twitch."
And other muscles are faster.
The reality of it is, and we don't have
a lot of data
on things like fiber type for our core
muscles, but we do have research going
you know, back to like the early 1990s
on autopsy models. So this is when we,
you know, unfortunately, folks come in
after they passed and we're able to look
at that.
And you're probably going to be pretty
surprised to realize that the vast
majority of the muscles in your core are
pretty much 50/50 fast twitch, slow
twitch.
Which is almost exactly what things like
your vastus lateralis in your quad
are.
And so let me ask you this.
If I started this conversation off by
saying, "Do you think that you should
train your core the exact same way you
train your quads?"
You'd be like, "No way."
But in fact, muscle fiber muscle fiber
type-wise,
they're very very similar.
And so now we're getting to the second
place. It's like, "Okay, well, wait a
minute. They're at they're activated a
lot,
but they're the same fiber type profile.
They have this anticipatory response.
And when you look around at the
research,
there's actually no literature at all
suggesting that the training principles
should differ in your abs
versus those in your quad. Okay, we've
already thrown a lot of people's thought
process out of whack here.
It's right back to what I talked about
at the beginning.
If I were to say,
"Do you want to train your quads for
growth?
Do you want to train your quads because
of knee pain or hip pain or do you want
to train them because you want to jump
higher?"
You would assume that the training
principles differ, right? So when we
start to break down the physiology and
the characteristics of the individual
core muscles themselves, we start to
realize
that's not a good rationale to train
them in this weird way where we do,
again, hundreds of repetitions per day,
we do them every day, we think that they
respond differently.
They are skeletal muscle. They're not a
different type of muscle. They're not a
different fiber type. They have a
slightly different function,
but they're not these these all day
activated
so because of that, they have to be
trained differently or they recover
faster or anything else like that. There
are some unique considerations that do
matter to training them. And
specifically what I'm referring to here
is the spinal health type of stuff. So
unlike your quad, where I can load it
really heavy and I can really isolate it
and smash it and not be too worried
about any other tissue getting hurt,
we don't have the same freedom with our
core.
So I can't have you do, for example,
five sets of one repetition
at your one rep core max.
I mean, I could, probably,
but my likelihood of causing an injury
or exacerbating an injury in our back or
hips is really really high. So, it's not
in the fibers or the muscle itself. It's
what's associated
with that tissue. It's what's around it,
and again, I'm specifically referring to
your spine here.
So, there is some evidence, and this is
controversial, but there is some
evidence that high repetition loading
with the lumbar spine um during
movements like like one can imagine
sit-ups and things like that has been
linked to elevated risk of injury. You
can see those data pretty clearly. At
the same time, and I actually was an
editor for um a pro-con piece many years
ago in uh Strength and Conditioning
Journal, where people were arguing back
and forth about whether or not the
crunchy or crunch exercise specifically
is safe or not.
You'll actually see evidence that it is
plenty safe.
If done appropriately, if done right,
flexion-based ab exercises
are not necessarily going to guarantee
back injury.
But, if you're coming from a perspective
or a population where you're trying to
either deal with somebody who has back
pain
or people that are consistently getting
it, I understand why you're super
sensitive to that exercise. You Many
people in that world do not like it
either because they've seen it cause
pain or they're thinking
there's just other ways I can train
those muscle groups. Why run the risk?
But, at the same time, that's not fair
then to throw the exercise out
completely and say things like it's
going to cause back pain. Hopefully,
that helps you understand a little bit
of why that exercise specifically, and
really what we're talking about is a
broader concept of should I train the ab
muscles more like my
quads and other muscles, or should I
have entirely different principles? And
what I'm generally trying to argue is
there are maybe some considerations,
but I don't think throwing everything
that we've ever known about training out
is the appropriate response either
because the data just aren't there. It
just does not indicate that that is
necessary.
Today's episode is sponsored by Eight
Sleep. Eight Sleep makes smart mattress
covers with cooling, heating, sleep
tracking, and more. Uh personally, I've
been sleeping on an Eight Sleep mattress
for more than 3 years now, and it's
absolutely glorious. I love it so much
that I hate traveling away from home
because I can't sleep on my Eight Sleep
Pod 5. As you'll hear me talk about
endlessly on this podcast, there's
really nothing you can do that makes
more of an impact on your health and
performance than getting a great night
of sleep. And getting great sleep
requires having your body temperature
drop a couple at night, and that's hard
to do on your own. The Eight Sleep has
been a game-changer for me because I run
hot at night, or as my wife calls it,
I'm a furnace. If I don't have something
like an Eight Sleep helping me cool
down, I'll wake up in the middle of the
night overheating and not feeling great.
This is something I've also found in
many people that I coach, especially
those who are really physically active.
The Pod 5 is the latest generation of
the Eight Sleep mattress covers, and it
can go on any mattress. Heats or cools
each side of the bed from 55° to 110° F,
and provides high-fidelity sleep
tracking. If you'd like to try Eight
Sleep, go to eightsleep.com/perform,
and use the code perform to save up to
$350
off your Pod 5 Ultra. You get 30 days to
try it at home and return it if you
don't love it, but I'm confident that
you will. I certainly love mine and
would never consider returning it. Eight
Sleep currently ships to the US, Canada,
the UK, and select countries in the EU,
and even Australia. Again, that's
eightsleep.com/perform,
and use the code perform to save up to
$350.
I think we can start jumping into
saying, "Okay,
I'm bought, I'm sold. I understand
there's different perspectives, and we
need to think about this differently if
I'm trying to maximize how I look or how
I feel or how I perform.
How do I know if my core is strong
enough? How do I test it? And then, what
do I do specifically to train based upon
these three goals?"
So, let's go ahead and jump into that
first part, which is and if you're a
long-time friend and listener of the
show, you know that I always like to do
my three eyes,
which is how do I investigate, how do I
interpret, and then how do I intervene?
And so, friends, here we go with our
very first eye, and that is how do I
investigate?
How do I measure? How do I know if my
core is strong enough?
Well, there's no direct answer here
because of some of the things I just
said.
You probably don't want to do a one
repetition max sit-up. I can't think of
a of a situation in which I've ever done
that. So, it's a little bit different
than your quads or your hamstrings.
But, you can take this from the same
perspective of is it a movement that I
want to test, or is it an actual muscle
itself?
Most people
will do movement type of testing. And
there's some common ones, some classic
ones.
You know, one I've used actually for for
for many years, we did all the testing
for the Anaheim Ducks, the hockey team,
as well as the LA Kings.
Uh this happened in our lab uh probably,
I don't know, 7 or 8 years in a row. And
we would do like this off-season
testing, all the players would come in,
and we would look at this. And one of
the tests we would always do
is called a Biering-Sørensen trunk
extension test. It's really cool. But,
imagine laying on your stomach on a
table, and then you scoot all the way
off the table till only your waist and
legs are on the table, and your upper
body is hanging off.
So, if you would just relax, your upper
body would fall forward, and your body
would be in like a 90° angle with your
head pointing towards the ground.
So, what the extension test does, and
it's really a muscular endurance test,
says, "Okay, raise your upper body up
until your entire body is parallel to
the ground, and hold it as long as you
can."
This test has been around since like
early 1980s. It's been there forever.
It's really pretty awesome. It's pretty
crude.
And it's again, it's not really a one
rep max test.
It is a test of functionality, and what
the assumption here is
if your muscular endurance
is low and you can't hold that position
for very long,
then we can make some assumptions about
your overall strength in your spinal
erectors and back extensor muscles.
And as I mentioned earlier, those are
critical components to your  core
strength.
So, that's a really, really common one.
It's also safe. I don't have to load
anything. I don't need technique and
warm-ups, and it's a pretty easy one
that's been used a lot.
You would also look into another classic
one's called the Sahrmann 5. Uh these
are like a it's a five-level core test
that can be done. And again, I'll put
some links up so you can go check it
out. I'm not going to walk you through
all of them.
But, it's things like level one, I
think, is a
uh laying on your back,
and you're going to raise one leg up
until your leg and your hip are both at
90°. So, you're laying on your back,
and you raise your hip up, and so your
femur is pointed directly in the air,
and then your shank is at a 90°. So, 90°
hips, 90°
and knees. Sorry, I got kind of wordy
there, but I think you follow me, right?
And you do one leg at a time. That's
kind of level one. You raise that first
one up, and then you raise that second
one up. And what you're looking for are
things like your low back.
In order to raise your leg up in the
air, does your low back have to come off
of the table that you're lying on?
Suggesting that the only way you get to
to true hip flexion
is by using like hip flexor muscles
rather than core muscles and things like
that. So, that's roughly what it's kind
of look at.
As I mentioned, there's like four
There's actually five levels to this.
With the highest level, I actually is
really hard.
It's a really cool double-leg thing. So,
imagine both legs are up. Uh so, you're
lying on your back, and your knees are
on your chest, and your calves are on
your hamstrings. So, you're like hugging
yourself.
You get to that 90/90 position, and then
you lower both legs at the same time
back down to the ground.
So, be without holding onto the sides of
the table, of course. Your hands, I
think, are on your chest or curled up.
This is actually really hard to do, and
you have to have a lot of core integrity
and strength to be able to lower them
both down. I think the technical thing
is like you got to be within 12 cm of
the table, and then you extend until
your entirely flat. I'm probably Again,
if I'm losing you on descriptions, you
can Google these things. The Sahrmann, S
A H R
M A N N. It's like the Sahrmann 5 and
other ones. There are dozens and dozens
and dozens of tests like this. This is
not an exhaustive list. From a
performance perspective,
those tests I just mentioned certainly
would qualify.
If you have a
access to a laboratory or if you're
looking at kind of a higher
gold standard grade here, you would look
at things like EMG. So, these are little
sensors we can put directly on the
muscle that tests its activation.
Most of the research in the ab and core
space uses EMGs. And the inference here
is a muscle that is activated more
is therefore working harder, stronger,
or better.
So, if you wanted more detail about the
precision activation of the muscles for
you, you're going to have to do
something like this. You could also look
at things like a Proteus machine. I know
this is a company that I have been
involved with in the past. We've uh put
some research out on doing rotation. It
is the only machine that I'm aware of,
and they're not very common. They're
hard to find.
But, you can actually do rotational
movements on this in a lot of different
ways, and you can get direct power
testing, velocity, and force outputs on
it.
I don't know of of Again, theoretically,
you could probably do this with any
machine that has a force transducer or
velocity transducer on it, but that's
the only
real one I know of that has that
information
directly on it.
So, again, maybe not something all of
you have to do. It is more difficult,
more challenging, but if you really
wanted to know what your rotational
power is or what your flexion or
extension powers are, you could do it on
a machine like the Proteus.
Lastly here is look. Unfortunately, and
as you'll see from the research here in
one moment, investigating muscle growth
for your core muscles is extraordinarily
challenging. There's very, very, very
little research on muscle growth
in this area.
You could, in theory, try to find an MRI
or an ultrasound machine, and I think
you're going to struggle.
What we have been doing more recently,
personally,
is I have a program actually called
Optima Muscle.
This uses a Springbok MRI technology and
it's actually reasonably affordable
for some.
It's pretty fast and you can get an MRI
scan done and it outlines the exact
volume and size
of over 140 muscles on your body.
And so you can look at symmetry, you can
look at fat infiltration. And you can
start to see things like this either at
a baseline
or as a pre and post, right? We did this
and we trained like this 6 months later,
did my core actually grow?
It's really unfortunate but you can't
measure your core muscles with a tape
measure.
You can't do like images are hard to do
because so much of how your core appears
is based upon your body weight and your
fat.
Most other muscles it's a little bit
easier, right? I can take a picture, I
can use a tape measure on your biceps
and triceps and deltoids and see if
they're bigger.
If you really want to know
the size of your obliques and your
spinal erectors,
the only thing again I am really aware
of is that type of MRI technology but
to be really clear, I have a conflict of
interest here. This is something I make
money on and and sell to people. So,
don't need to do it.
Plenty of you can get everything you
need from your core and abs doing those
functional tests
or any other thing that we've used
before. From an investigation
perspective, I don't want to go much
further. That's about all we have and
again if you have a specific need or
desire, you can look up other tests to
perform. I would actually rather move
directly past interpretation and go
right into intervention and start
talking about which exercises we select,
the order we do them in, the frequency,
the intensity, the volume, the rest
intervals and then how to successfully
progress these exercises because as I've
mentioned several times now, the
progression strategy
in concept, in theory should be the same
as progression for any other muscle
but we do have practical and realistic
considerations to make
that tell us we may should have a
different style of progression.
All right, you've collected these data,
you've run some tests. Now, how do we
properly interpret these?
Well, I hesitated to do this part
because I want to make sure all of you
continue to train your abs regardless of
how you score.
But that said, let's take some context
in the results. I'm going to run the
gamut from scientific information and
evidence to what I actually personally
like and I'll distinguish when I'm doing
the former versus the latter.
First off is that classic Sarma test.
Generally, if you're at level three or
lower,
this is what I would personally call
highly problematic. You're probably
experiencing back pain or
really close to it.
So, I would spend a lot of time as a
primary focus if you're at that. If
you're at a four or a five,
I would personally like to see five
always and I guess maybe to clarify,
these are typically not scored in terms
of force output or duration of time.
These are simply can you execute the
exercise
without that low back moving off of the
platform. So, it's pass fail kind of
stuff. So, I want to see a five
realistically.
Four is probably more common at best.
Below three,
we're making uh our movement and our
core and abs a very very high priority
in our training program.
The other exercise I mentioned, the back
extension test,
the number you're going to see there, I
think the original number was like 178
seconds.
Such that if you scored below that,
then you were increased likelihood of
having low back pain. And I think the
top end number is 200 seconds. So, if
you score
and hold that position for longer than
200 seconds, so you're talking,
you know, 3 and 1/2 minutes here,
that you're less likely to be
experiencing back pain. None of these
can tell you 100% if you're going to
have back pain or don't but again, it's
more or less likely.
Most of the time,
you're going to cut that test off at 4
minutes.
So, if you're anywhere over 200 to 240
seconds, you're probably going to, you
know, check that box and say if you do
have back pain,
it's not because of low back or any of
our extensor muscles
muscular endurance or fatigue.
Some other things I can give you that
are, you know, again, my personal
experience and not necessarily
scientifically supported or extremely
thoroughly supported.
And these are things like do you
actually have active control of your
transverse abdominis? So, can you pull
your abs inward?
This might sound silly or like, of
course I can.
But many people can't or they can but
it's very very minimal.
So, this is an anti pass or fail. Right?
I'm just going to judge this based on my
eye. Can you really move it in?
You don't have to be in that position
where we can pull our
abs so far in that it looks like, you
know, there's an inch difference between
our anterior side of our stomach and and
our back. But we should have some good
separation between our rib cage and
ability to pull our stomach in.
You can do this in a couple of different
ways.
You could do this seated. So, can I pull
my stomach in, pull my belly button in
closer to my spine when I'm seated? Many
many people will struggle with that.
Sometimes it's easier to actually go on
a quadruped position, so on your hands
and knees,
because your stomach will fall to the
ground. It actually puts external
pressure on it and then we'll ask, can
you pull it back up and in?
And more people will probably have
success with that.
Even if they're not good at it, it's a
really good test, it's a really good way
to actually train just to say, can you
activate and control that?
I don't have exact numbers on how far it
should go.
You get the idea. This is this more of
like a can you pass or fail?
Another one like that that I enjoy
and use very frequently
is the obliques side of the equation.
So, if you take your two hands and you
make an L
with your hands so that your thumb is,
you know, pointed sideways and your
fingers pointing up, just like you'd
make an L with your finger.
And you put those on your sides just
above your hip.
Can you move your hands outward
without, in fact, those of you watching,
you can see I'm doing this as I'm
talking. There's a small change in my
voice
but I should have active control
of my obliques and my transverse
abdominis so that I can move my hands
outward while still having a breath,
while not having to hold, not having to
contract and have everything tight.
Can I activate those things separately?
So again,
a way you can make this easier
is you crunch down. So, imagine you're
trying to connect your fingertips and
your thumbs and you're smashing your
sides together.
And when you do that, just like the
quadruped version,
you're more likely to be able to do some
contraction. If you go from normal to
just pushing out, very few people have
success there.
Similar thing can be done from the
posterior side. So, putting your
fingertips just above what's called your
PSIS, so that little kind of top bone in
the back of your pelvis, can you push it
backwards and out?
If you can, we have a better ability to
brace in a 360° fashion
rather than just getting all of our
bracing strategy from the front side and
locking down
or overextending.
So, that's a combination of, you know,
again, kind of back of the envelope
things I personally like to see
in contrast to the the direct numbers to
hit to understand whether you're kind of
good, bad or indifferent. So, that's a
little bit of context of how to
interpret
the results from the tests that you're
doing.
I don't think we need to go much further
here because I actually would like to
spend the rest of our time getting into
our third eye and that's intervene.
How do we manipulate these modifiable
variables? How do we choose the
exercises? How do we order them? How do
we pick our volume and intensity and our
rest intervals? And then how do we
progress them? As we've discussed a
little bit in the physiology section of
the conversation,
they do have unique requirements. The
physiology is not quite different but
they are other things we need to
associate with that will interact with
and alter how we take our progression
style. We still want to progressively
overload but we need to think about it a
little bit differently for our abs and
our core relative to some of our other
muscles. So, let's go ahead and do that
stuff right now.
The first stop I want to make is just
getting on the same page with what a
core exercise actually is. By now, we
know the difference between core and abs
but more specifically, these are often
described as things like isolation
exercises versus functional or versus
dynamic or in the literature, you're
going to see these sometimes called
integrated exercises.
So, the isolated or the abs specific
exercises are your planks, your back
extensions, your side bends.
Colloquially, if you just think about
this as exercises I'm doing primarily to
target my abs, that is the the optimal
target.
The other side, the dynamic, the
movement, the integrated exercises are
ones that activate, utilize, strengthen,
enhance my abs
but they're also doing something else in
larger.
These are deadlifts, overhead presses,
lunges, carries, pushes and things like
that.
A lot of research, these are fantastic
for your abs.
Where people will disagree, and earlier
in the episode I gave the perspective of
like the powerlifting or weightlifting
or strongman,
they tend to default to saying, hey, I'm
doing these big dynamic movements. I'm
doing carries and
walks and stuff like that. My core is
going nuts, the research supports that.
These are very very good at activating
your core.
Where the problem lies is, therefore, I
don't need to do any of these core
isolation exercises and the research
would actually suggest that's probably
incorrect.
The other Pilates type of equation and
no offense to all my Pilates girls and
guys out there,
but they have a little bit of the
opposite approach, which is to say,
if I want to get my core done, I need to
do a bunch of different core isolation
exercises.
One of the things that we know here is
if you were to look at the research and
you look at the reviews and the
meta-analyses,
we need a lot more work in this area.
It's actually
There's not a lot here. There's enough,
but we need a lot more.
In general, based upon the evidence we
have right now though,
you will typically see that free weights
and suspension type of exercises
will activate core musculature more so
than isolated exercises.
That said, you will also see
those free weights and suspension
exercises alone
do not sufficiently cover the core
musculature.
Really easy then to say the obvious
answer most likely
is to do a combination of those big free
weight movements,
probably some suspension exercises, and
then certainly some independent
isolation exercises.
Suspension exercises, if you're not
familiar,
think about things like being in a
push-up position
and then instead of having your feet on
the ground, you have your feet in the
loops of a TRX band
or have them on a stability ball or some
other place that
puts your feet up in a in a different
position. What we need to think about
is, okay,
I probably need to think about all of
these in most of my programs, but I can
spend more or less time
on one side of that equation depending
on the goal,
which I'll get into
directly. One of the things you'll also
see some some evidence for in the
research is that after you've gotten
reasonably trained,
the isolated exercises
don't necessarily work as well as they
used to.
So, early in your training journey,
whether it's been a long time, you've
taken some time off, or you've never
exercised and you're just starting, you
might be fine simply doing the isolation
exercises. But after you've reached a
certain level of fitness,
strength,
activation ability,
it's probably going to behoove you to
move on past that. Now, whether or not
you still continue to do some isolation
exercises, that's fine,
but if you only stick to those,
again, the current research would
indicate that you're leaving potential
gains in performance and aesthetics on
the table by only staying with the
isolated exercises.
And just while we're here, examples of
isolation exercises, again, these would
be your classic core exercises, your
planks, your back extensions, your side
bends. These things These are isolating
the the ab or core muscles
and either not using other larger
muscles and appendages or using them
very minimally. So, that's really what
we mean. Isolated doesn't necessarily
mean isometric and not moving.
It just means you're you're targeting
those cores. And I'll explain really
quickly here
why that actually matters and why those
don't work as well as those bigger
exercises
because of my very next point, which is
the one thing you'll see really
consistent here.
The key driving principle
in effective ab or core exercises
is contraction intensity.
So, if you can contract your abs really
hard with
a body weight movement
or an external load or a machine,
it's clearly telling you those things
were not the variables that mattered.
What mattered is you simply got yourself
in a position where you were safe,
you didn't get hurt, and you were able
to contract really really hard.
That's the key differentiator and it is
clear as day once you go through all the
literature.
That is the thing that always has to be
there to work.
If it's not there, it doesn't work, and
how you choose to get to high intensity
is really up to you.
What we're talking about here is a great
example of what's called the size
principle.
So, the size principle says that you
have these motor units. So, this is all
the motor neurons in your body and then
the motor units in the muscle that they
activate.
When you start to produce a human
movement, you will always start with
what are called low threshold motor
units.
These tend to, but are not always, slow
twitch motor units. They tend to, but
are not always, are smaller. But they
are the ones that are more energetically
efficient.
And when you need more force demands,
the way that your body increases force
output
is that you turn more of these motor
units on.
You may be actually surprised, but you
don't have the ability to regulate force
production at the level of muscle.
Such as to say, at the individual muscle
fiber itself, you can't contract it at
60% or 70%. When a muscle fiber
contracts, it contracts at full force.
That's the only option it has. It's all
or none principle, all or none. So, only
way that you up or down regulate force
output is you turn on more or turn off
more of these units.
So,
when you don't do activities that
require high force, you don't activate
the high threshold motor units
because they are exclusively reserved
for very high force demand.
And so, we see this as a consistent
principle across all skeletal muscle and
it holds true in the abs and core as
well.
If I told you right now
that we wanted to get your quad
stronger, and I'll keep coming back to
this parallel,
and you said, yes, I want to maximize my
muscle size in my quad, I want the
biggest quads ever, or I want to break a
world record in leg extension strength
or something, and I said, awesome.
We're going to do wall squats.
You'd be like, what?
Like, awesome exercise, great for
muscular endurance,
but no one in the history of the world
who got the biggest quads ever,
you know, Platz didn't do wall squats
only, and powerlifters You get the point
here.
Not saying you can't do them,
but if that's your only approach,
you're going to be very hard to convince
any athlete or coach that that is the
best way.
That's the same thing you're doing with
your abs when all you're doing are
planks
and three sets of 20 crunches.
You're forgetting the size principle,
which is huge numbers of your motor
units are not being activated. When
they're not activated, you don't
actually get stronger. You get better
endurance, but you don't get them
stronger.
The equivalent here exchange would be,
yeah, sure, do your wall squats, where
you're holding that 45° position against
the wall, and then also add in some leg
presses or leg extensions or whatever
leg exercise you like. All right,
fatigue and burning are not the same as
force production.
There's an overlap, of course, but you
see the major difference here. The
problem is, as we've mentioned, it's
really hard to load up your rectus
abdominis. Like it is easy to load up
your quads on a leg press machine. I
can't put 400 lb on a side bend. It
doesn't work, right? I can't hold
even maybe 50 or 60 lb in front of me
and do a a Russian twist. Like it's just
very difficult for most people to do.
So again, principles are the same, but
we have to think about the loading
strategies a little bit differently, but
we need to get to loading strategies. In
fact, I'll be so bold as to say most
people who do not see progress, whether
that be aesthetics or in strength,
in their ab
or core muscles, it's because they're
forgetting to add load or forgetting to
progress with intensity.
The general strategy we see here is
always either do it longer, add more
seconds, add more minutes to my hold, or
do more repetitions.
Those are fine. Those do represent
progression,
but there's an entire other pathway
here,
and it turns out your core muscles and
abs respond better to that strategy than
only using more time duration and
fatigue management.
And so, when we think about these
dynamic movements
and we compare these to our sit-ups,
if I know that the load matters a ton,
it's far safer and easier for me to put
a several hundred pounds on a sled
and push it
than it is for me to put several hundred
pounds on and try to do that sit-up. And
so, again, make sure you're tracking
with me here.
If I know I have to get the rectus
abdominis and transverse abdominis and
and your internal and external obliques
to contract at its highest force
capacity,
and I can do that
by putting hundreds and hundreds of
pounds
onto a barbell and doing a squat with it
or a deadlift, I can actually get that
muscle to activate more, to turn on and
produce more force
than I can
with a side bend because of the
limitations in loading the side bend.
Does that distinction make sense?
That's why these big movements are
critical
to maximizing ab and core development.
It's not the fact that they're isolating
your core any more or less,
it's that they are a safer way
to maximize their force contraction
ability.
It causes fatigue and training in other
areas,
but that's really the only way we can
push intensity and force demands of our
core muscle that doesn't put our spine
and our hips at tremendous risk.
Today's episode is sponsored by David.
David makes protein bars unlike any I
have ever encountered. They have an
amazing 28 g of protein, only 150
calories, and 0 g of sugar. That's
right. 28 g of protein and 75% of its
calories come from that protein. This is
50% higher than the next closest protein
bar. Honestly, it's the best tasting bar
I've ever had in my life by a mile. And
their newest bar, the David Bronze Bar,
tastes incredible as well. While I often
talk about the importance of getting 1 g
of protein per pound of body weight for
things like muscle health and recovery
and the promotion of lean body mass and
satiety, the reality of that is for most
people getting that 1 g of protein per
pound of body weight is really
challenging. However, David makes that
easy. Their bars taste incredible. The
gold bar is packed with 28 g of protein
with just 150 calories and the bronze
bar has 20 g of protein also with just
150 calories. I eat one almost every
single day and always have two or three
with me in my backpack when I'm
traveling and I'm like literally mean
always. It probably sounds funny but I
eat them as dessert all the time. When
you try them you'll know exactly what I
mean. If you're interested in trying
these bars for yourself you can go to
davidprotein.com/perform.
Again, that's davidprotein.com/perform.
What are some direct examples? I'm going
to give you some exercises that you'll
see commonly that are based on the
movement patterns as well as the muscles
themselves. So whether you're in this
thing and you're choosing again your
exercises based on movement patterns or
muscles you'll have some options and I'm
not going to go through all these
though I will make more available in the
show notes.
So from a movement perspective again
remember we're looking at flexion, we're
looking at lateral flexion, we're
looking at extension and rotation and
then of course
the anti-movement in all of those areas.
So as easy example one we've been using
very very commonly the classic flexion
exercise are the crunches or the
sit-ups. There's also things like
jackknives and and other you know get
your feet closer to your head kind of
scenarios. There's also then the
anti-flexion exercises.
These are far less common. You maybe
have never done any of these or done a
small amount of them. But these are
things like the Pallof
posterior hold. So the Pallof spelled p
a l l o f exercise again you can look
that up. And it's the the posterior or
the back kind of version of that. You'll
also see things like a supine plank. So
for those of you that remember
a little bit of your biomechanics if I
were to take your hands and hold your
palms up to the sky like you're holding
a bowl of soup and you don't want to
spill it that's what supine is. And if
you put your palms down to the ground
that would be pronation.
So a supine plank is when you're
actually the opposite. So you're on your
back
and you're facing up in the air and then
you're holding that. So remember
you're doing anti-flexion. You're not
flexing up but you're avoiding
unnecessary flexion. You can do the same
thing in a suspended fashion. So you
could do a suspended supine plank.
From a lateral flexion perspective this
is your side planks, your hip dips. Some
people do these on a physioball or a
Swiss ball and you can do like a side
crunch or some people call these you
know oblique v-ups or oblique sit-ups
and you can just kind of imagine this
lateral flexion.
The anti-version is is probably
a little bit easier to understand than
the anti-flexion.
Anti-lateral flexion are
holding that thing from moving sideways.
So this is a side plank with a row. So
imagine being in a side plank position
and then you're actually with a cable
and you're rowing it to yourself.
You could simply do a lateral plank as
well. You could do a suspended lateral
plank. And so in that particular case
imagine you're on your side
and your feet are you know in a TRX
band.
And let's just say you're on your right
shoulder. Your right elbow's on the
ground. What's happening is you're not
actively flexing but you're stopping
your side from dipping and hitting the
ground. So you're avoiding unwanted
lateral movement.
That's the the anti-version here.
If it's easier for you to think about
anti
core exercises as simply eccentric
or avoiding eccentric movement that's
fine too. Right? But you're not actively
moving you're avoiding movement in this
case.
You could also think of them as like
slight plays on isometric exercises.
Similar thing. If none of that made
sense don't worry about it. Just keep
thinking of the anti-movement.
So that's flexion and lateral flexion.
Then we have extension. So this these
are your supermans. You're laying on
your stomach and you're lifting your
quads and your stomach and your ribs up
in the air and you're flying like
Superman through the air.
Back extensions, reverse
hyperextensions, straight bridges, Swiss
ball bridges, Swiss ball reverse
crunches like there's reverse extensions
rather like there's all kinds of
variations
of this stuff. The anti-version would be
things like the Pallof hold. So again
you're kind of going up there and you're
holding that position.
The prone planks or remember supine and
prone so now you're in the opposite
position. You're up and holding.
Could do it with suspension as well.
And so forth.
And then finally the rotation exercises.
More advanced versions like windshield
wipers or Russian twists.
So on and so forth. The anti-versions of
this would be again various Pallof holds
or supine lying Pallof holds and so on
and so forth.
If again you're all at all like what was
that specific exercise
none of these are special.
So you could Google n a anti-rotation
movement, pick the one that you like the
most play with different ones. I
actually use a large large large variety
of these.
My favorite rotation exercise currently
is imagine having a cable.
And that cable is set up at about you
know you kind of a mid-rib range.
And then I spread my feet out really
really really wide
and I have a bar or a rope on the cable.
And I stand horizontal to that. And so
you can imagine
the machine is to my right and I'm you
know facing a different direction. My
head is away from it.
And then I'll rotate my upper body,
reach to grab the cable and then rotate
my upper body and pull the cable and the
rope in front of my body all the way to
the other side. If you're watching this
video you you can see me kind of moving
that way. My lower body does not rotate.
So my feet stay forward, my feet stay
wide and I just pull straight in front
of me from the right side to the left
side and then eccentrically I slowly let
it go backwards. I have no idea why but
this feels phenomenal for me. My
obliques light up. My back feels great.
Core is all over. It I just feel
awesome.
I don't know if you like that exercise
as much as I do but
I don't know any research behind that. I
just think it's a great exercise. So
there's tons and tons and tons of
creative ways to go about these things.
I don't want you overly fixated on the
exercise choice.
What you want you to think about is
which movement pattern am I going after?
Flexion, extension, rotation so forth.
Anti or movement based.
And then finding any number of exercises
that fit that pattern and experimenting.
Find the one that you like where you
feel the great contraction cuz it's
impossible for me to predict and tell
you which ones
you'll like. For example the one I just
gave you. Some of you might hate that.
Be like I don't feel this at all or I
don't like it or whatever the case is.
So because there's so many exercises
here I don't want to get too bogged down
on the specific exercises and walking
you through you know how to do each
individual one.
It's the concepts and the movement
patterns we want to go after.
If you're programming based on the
muscles themselves rather than the
movement pattern it's a little bit
simpler to explain.
Rectus abdominis is pretty
straightforward. We've been over this
multiple times now. It is weighted
cables. It is crunches and reverse
crunches. It's leg raises. It's ab
wheels. It's rollouts.
It's you know various exercises like
that. The obliques
any type of rotation, any type of
anti-rotation. So the Pallof press
the wood chops, the suitcase carries,
the planks
all these going to target the obliques.
The transverse abdominis
remember it's not rotation. It's pulling
the belly in. This is when your dead
bugs
pull perfect. This is when your stir the
pot exercises. You know so you're
say your hand both of your forearms are
on a physioball or a Swiss ball and
you're rotating you know clockwise or
counterclockwise and you're you know
quote unquote stirring the pot. So this
is causing you to pull your abdominals
in while you're making movement and
you're avoiding unnecessary and unwanted
movement. Those are more effective.
I'm sorry to say this for the third or
fourth time now but it's really
important point.
It's the forward and backward stuff that
tends to be best for your rectus
abdominis not the rotation. So just
think about it that way. So if you're
programming for the muscle that's really
as far and as complicated as you as you
have to go.
With that basic information I want to go
directly into specific considerations
for looking versus feeling versus
performing. And let's start off of
course
with our look.
So if you're primarily here
because you want your abs to look better
I have to say something we have not yet
acknowledged and that is the fact that
the vast majority of aesthetic
appearance in your core is simply a body
fat body composition story which is a
nice way of saying you know your abs are
made in the kitchen not the gym.
100% true.
Maybe we'll come back on another episode
or listen to one of our prior episodes
on fat loss to talk about that but I
really want to stay focused today on
just the training aspect of it. So yes,
the best way to have more defined more
visible abs is to have very little fat
particularly around your core.
But that said what are the training
implications if either you've got the
nutrition down or you don't care about
it quite yet or whatever the case is.
I said this earlier but there's actually
very little research
on which types of exercises or training
protocols are best for muscle growth of
the core. We got a lot of that for your
arms and legs and everywhere else but we
just don't have it for your core muscles
most.
So that said this is when we have to
default to basic training strategies. I
went through that time before to set up
the fact that physiologically
it's very very similar to your other
muscles so that we have no rationale to
think that for muscle growth our
training protocols differ for our core.
What's that mean? You're looking at rest
intervals of anything you want.
There's excellent research. Muscle
growth is equal whether you use short
rest intervals, say 30 seconds between
sets,
or you lose use long rest intervals, up
to three plus minutes between sets.
So, you can do either approach there. In
terms of a frequency,
this is going to throw a lot of people
off.
You don't necessarily have to and you
probably don't want to train your core
if you're trying to maximize its growth
more than two to four times per week per
muscle group.
I just don't think we have any evidence
in the in the evidence we do have would
suggest
you probably don't want to train these
muscles every single day.
It doesn't work best for any other
muscle. It probably doesn't work best
for our ab muscles, either.
I should have also mentioned this a
second ago,
but while body fat will, of course, make
your abs more visible,
making them larger will, as well. So, we
don't want to just ignore our abs. If
you want a better looking stomach, you
should consider training to get bigger
ab muscles, but you do want to have
maybe some special considerations.
Because the rectus abdominis is
prominent, it is reasonable to say you
want to put as much, if not more,
emphasis on that muscle group than
somebody in the in the perform or feel
category. So, that's a unique difference
here. You should do more rectus
abdominis work.
You can program by movement, but you
should definitely make sure you're
programming by muscle group here, as
well.
You also want to
train rigorously your obliques because,
as I said at the beginning, this will
actually pull kind of the waistline in
and make it look like you've got this
shredded side.
So, we want to train them. We want to
train them with the same principles. You
can use whatever rest interval you like.
You can probably train the muscles,
you know, two to four times per week.
And you want to use, you know, that
classic 10 to 20 working sets
per muscle per week.
Split this up however you'd like.
You want to train hard.
Something like one to two reps in
reserve. So, this means at the end of
every set, you could feel like you could
maybe do one more rep, maybe two at the
most,
but not more than that.
So, it's got to be to failure or really
close to it.
And like every other muscle, you need to
have some form of progressive overload.
And as we just described, more reps is
not necessarily the only or best
approach to that.
The exercise choice you select,
I'm giving you some insights a second
ago and I apologize for kind of bouncing
around a little bit here,
but what you also might want to consider
is the unique
effects of the transverse abdominis. So,
because it is that built,
and you'll see this actually pretty
commonly
in women postpartum.
They feel like they have this little
pooch
or they're like, "Man, I'm lean again,
but this thing is sticking out." Well,
because the transverse abdominis pulls
your stomach back in, by working that,
you might be able to get yourself close
to that appearance of a flatter stomach.
So, do not disregard the transverse
abdominis even for aesthetics, even
though you can't see it directly.
A real critical missing component for a
lot of people who are failing this cuz
you're doing all RA work, right? You're
doing the sit-ups and the crunches in
there and maybe you're doing some side
bends.
You're not doing rotation, but you're
not doing anything for the transverse
abdominis, so it's having a harder time
kind of pulling that stuff in and tight.
Other weird considerations here are
things like your posture.
For example,
if you have
tight or however you want to phrase
this, hip flexor muscles, soas major,
and it pulls you into anterior tilt, so
it pulls your hips forward,
especially if this means it flares your
rib cage up,
or if you have an underdeveloped
diaphragm,
or a combination of these,
you might actually look like you have a
more rounded, more distended stomach
when you actually don't. And so, this is
a case, and I've seen this work, where
when you correct those things,
the abs, quote unquote, look better,
even though you actually didn't lose any
weight and you actually didn't add any
muscle size there, but you simply
corrected that position. If you don't
know what I'm talking about, just just
exaggerate it. Like flare your hips way
up in the air, arch your back really,
really, really hard, and you'll notice
your stomach shoots way out.
And then do the opposite. Kind of like
tuck your tailbone underneath you, pull
your ribs down,
and you'll realize, well, I'm pretty
flat there.
So, if you're in one of those
exaggerated or or poor positions,
simply actually moving that around and
and getting into a more neutral spine
position
might be a part of your equation if
you're here exclusively or primarily
for looks.
In kind of summarizing this group up and
finishing it, we do have,
I don't know, six or so studies that
have actually directly looked at either
ultrasound or MRI-based imaging of
muscles in the core. And what you're
typically going to see is a magnitude of
effect
that's pretty similar to other ones. So,
depending on the study you look at,
you're going to see rectus abdominis can
grow by, you know, and grow being
defined as as muscle thickness,
by 10 to 20%.
Those are pretty common. Um a lot of the
research here are in these kind of weird
models where they put electrical
um devices on your stomach and contract
your muscles for you.
And, you know, there's various different
models for that.
There's also been that there was
actually a series of classic direct
Pilates studies. There has been studies
in uh normative obese core population or
normative weight, sorry, obese
populations and and foam rollers. And
like there's this is kind of like weird
combination of research, but if you
smash it all together, you're going to
see
again, on average, about a 10 to 20%
increase in muscle thickness.
So, I know the core can grow.
And what you'll see across these studies
that are all, you know, six to eight to
12 weeks,
and whether they're using MRIs or
ultrasounds is
when you do the right training
principles,
these muscles grow
just like everything else.
And right training principles here is
defined as
not hundreds or thousands of
repetitions, not daily, but more
traditional muscle hypertrophy
programming styles.
So, that's the state of the research.
Now, I've never
focused my career on aesthetics. I don't
coach bodybuilders or fitness
competitors and and never really have,
but I personally am of the opinion,
based upon the evidence that we
currently have, that if the primary goal
here is good-looking abs,
I would recommend choosing a roughly
50/50 split-ish
between those big, complicated,
complex movements and the isolated ones.
I think this gives you the ability to
load them properly
to maximize the size principle, to get
force production done and drive
mechanical tension. This is the primary
driver of muscle hypertrophy. It also
allows you to keep the volume down
directly on your core and your spine.
At the same time, I would incorporate a
lot of these isolation exercises
because of the opposite. Your legs and
your arms might be already tired from
something else.
And so, by doing the isolation
exercises, we can make sure that the
rectus abdominis gets target or the
transverse abdominis, and we're not
failing because our quads got tired.
We're not failing because of some other
load reason. So, I think it's pretty
good rationale here to say
use a combination of those big dynamic
ones and the isolation exercises to
maximize the aesthetic appeal
of them. I would also make sure I'm
doing a combination of movement-based
exercises as well as the anti-movement
ones.
The anti-movement ones are, again, nice
because you can do a lot of them
and you're not doing a lot of increased
risk or load on your spine, which should
help you lower your risk of injury or
even mild aggravation.
So, from an exercise choice perspective,
that's what I would recommend.
Today's episode is sponsored by Element.
Element is an electrolyte drink that has
an ideal electrolyte
ratio of sodium, potassium, and
magnesium, but no both physical and
mental. And countless studies have shown
that even a slight degree of
dehydration, even as small as 1%, can
lead to decreases in physical output and
mental performance. We also know that
electrolytes are critical to proper
hydration, which I've been harping on
for years.
But you can do that, proper hydration,
by only drinking water, especially if
you sweat a lot. You need to get the
right amount of electrolytes in the
right ratios, and that's why I'm a huge
fan of Element. In fact, many of you
might remember that I featured Element
in my YouTube series on hydration nearly
6 years ago. I featured Element in these
videos because their blend of 1,000 mg
of sodium, 200 mg of potassium, and 60
mg of magnesium really is unique and
different than any other electrolyte on
the market and it has great scientific
support. I use Element on nearly a daily
basis, especially when I'm doing really
hard training in the heat and I'm
sweating a lot. If you'd like to try
Element, you can go to
drinklmnt.com/perform
to claim a free Element sample pack with
the purchase of any Element drink mix.
Again, that's drinklmnt.com/perform
to claim a free sample pack.
So, with that out of the way, let's
transition and talk about those that are
primarily focused on getting their core
to perform at its best.
There is actually a lot of research
here.
Very similar principles. You can still
go back to rest intervals. You can
really use any, but we're probably
looking at higher, right? Because when
we induce a lot of fatigue,
we can't load, we can't load, we can't
activate as much, and we're not getting
to the spot we need to be at. So,
probably, personally,
hedging more on the minute to two or
more minutes of rest intervals between
sets.
We're looking at three to 5 days per
week, very similar to normal traditional
strength protocols. You know, 6 to 15
working sets per muscle group per week.
You know, one to two, but probably
closer to one repetition reserve.
With, you know, some strategic and
intentional
uh progression strategies.
So, this could look like something where
instead of doing a 50/50 split between
the big exercises and the isolation, I'm
probably leaning more like 75% big, 25%
uh structured core exercises.
Because that research is so clear that
the big exercises activate the core
more. And since that's what I'm trying
to do, I'm using the core exercises to
become a better athlete or to improve my
movement, I don't necessarily need to
maximize the RA itself. I need to make
sure that the RA is strong enough to
hold tension so that other body parts
can move, that it can avoid unnecessary
movement, but I don't need it to look a
certain way. I don't necessarily need it
to grow at all. So, a little bit of a
difference here.
We can go all the way back to the very
beginning. And remember when I teased
with some of those questions?
I'm not going to answer them directly
right now, but I think and I'm hoping
you can answer them for yourself. And
don't worry, at the end I will directly
answer them if you still haven't figured
it out.
But, looking at the research that has
directly compared different types of
activities,
you will see squats and deadlifts and
carries and sled work and overhead
presses
often times activate the core muscles
more than the isolation exercises. And
since we know we're using this as a
means to transfer force from one part of
the body to the other, it just makes
more intuitive sense
to focus on that.
I've made that point several times, so I
think we can actually move past that a
little bit
and get directly into our third
category, and that's feel.
And again, I'm usually using this as a
euphemism to say
spinal health, back pain, or avoiding
those things.
Of the three categories, this has by far
the most research, and it makes sense.
There's a lot more people in back pain.
In fact, you hear wild stats like 80% of
people will experience low back pain at
some point in their life, and like 50 to
60% are experiencing it chronically. So,
we should have probably a lot more
research here than we have on uh which
exercises transfer to football better.
Makes sense.
We're probably now going the other end
of the spectrum, where we might do, you
know, 75 or 80% isolation exercises and,
you know, 20 to 25% the big exercises
because we have direct intention now.
We want to be a little more cautious,
and we need to ensure exact movement
patterns are doing what they're supposed
to be doing because we're trying to
correct dysfunction. And we need to make
sure that individual muscle groups
themselves are not underutilized or
lacking function.
This is a situation where we can go more
frequently. If you want to go every
single day here,
it's okay because we're not progressing
these with intensity
very often. We're not trying to go
really, really, really heavy with them.
We're generally, by definition, choosing
exercises
that I can't actually load that heavy
anyways. And we're often times using it
as a neural grooving pattern. So, I'm
trying to establish either pain
desensitization or activation or small
blood flow changes. So, more frequently
matters. No one ever got overtrained by
doing bird dogs every day. Right? So, we
we just don't have any real risk there
because the load and intensity are
actually, you know, pretty minimal. But,
we can still chase fatigue.
We can induce certainly some strength
gains. We can induce some muscle growth,
and then we can actually restore some
functionality.
So, you can do as little these as little
as, you know, 3 days a week up to, you
know, 7 days a week.
You can do a lot of working sets, you
know, up to even maybe 30 working sets
per week per muscle.
You can, you know, get much closer. You
can take these to full volitional
fatigue, right? You can take these until
you're getting as burned as you possibly
want
and not worry about, you know, again,
overloading some tissue.
If at this point we look back to the
very beginning and we go, "Oh, okay.
That's why my physical therapist
recommended these exercises or
programmed it this way. But, that's why
my bodybuilding coach said to do this."
Or the person I follow online
said this exercise was terrible or love,
and
every combination in between. So, I hope
at this point
you have some clarity
and some relief, and you can think about
where you're at now or when situations
pop up in the future, and you can start
to go, "Okay. Well, now I'm going to
modify my core training, either ramp it
up
or actually maybe even peel it back, do
different styles, do different
intensities, do different rep ranges, do
different exercise choices
based upon the actual demands and needs
that I have." I think it would be
helpful though to give you maybe a
particular example.
And so, if you're up for it, I'll just
give you one right now, and I'll kind of
walk you through what a sample week
could look like. At the highest level,
I'm probably always going to pick at
least one exercise from the flexion, one
from the rotation, and then one from
each of those in the anti. So, four
unique categories,
not necessarily every day, but certainly
every week.
I will rarely pick a muscle group
specific exercise. I almost default to
movement. But, if you want to pick a
little bit more or in addition to that
based on the muscle group, that's fine,
too. So, it might look something like
this.
Say you want to do your abs
or something in your core five or six
days per week.
You could mix and match, and you could
say something like day one,
I'm going to do heavier load,
six to 12 reps,
two to three working sets, and go heavy.
And I'm really chasing stability here.
So, I want to make sure that my core can
be really stable when I get things
really heavy.
Great. So, because you're going heavier,
you're going to do less repetitions per
set and probably less total working
sets. And then I might pick, again,
one exercise from each of those broad
categories. So, maybe we start with an
anti-extension exercise, and I pick an
ab wheel or a dead bug,
and I load it. I know that these
exercises are going to be really high in
RA and TVA activation,
but my spine is not getting overloaded.
I'm not I don't have a barbell on my
back. I'm not flexing or extending with
really heavy loads because I'm on my
back. And so, maybe I'm carrying and
holding a really, really heavy, maybe a
50 or 60-lb kettlebell, and I'm doing my
dead bugs with that.
So, I know all of you have probably done
dead bugs, but most of you have probably
done them with just your body weight.
But, you can load it, too. You can put
load ankle weights on, or you could use
bands, or you can add additional
resistance where it's actually
failing because of closer to heavy than
it is because you did 50 repetitions.
All with great technique, of course. So,
we've knocked out anti-extension. We
focused on prioritizing stability, but
we went heavier.
One exercise there.
Then we add maybe an anti-rotation
anti-lateral flexion exercise,
or where we're looking on stability, but
it's actually dynamic stability. So, in
the case of the dead bug,
everything is being locked down. Like,
nothing is moving except for arms and
legs. The core is completely still.
Where if we do something like a suitcase
carry,
so if you're not familiar with this
exercise, imagine carrying uh a really
heavy dumbbell on one side and walking.
And so, your core is actually doing a,
you know, a   dynamic
exercise, a human movement,
while you're externally loading one
side. And so, your your body has to work
to not fall to that side of the weight.
So, it's anti-lateral flexion, and it's
also anti-rotation because you actually
have to rotate your your core to walk,
but because the load is there, it's
going to want to rotate it more than you
need. And so, you have to avoid
unnecessary rotation.
So, again,
another thing you could load really,
really heavy. You could take this to as
heavy as your grip will allow, and what
you're doing is not training your grip,
per se. You're training your ability to
move with a non-bending body and a
non-over-rotating body, and you're just
going to walk.
Really, really hard, great for your
core, but you're not going to get a lot
of systemic fatigue from that.
But, it allows you to go heavy for six
to 12 reps.
And then maybe you pick one other
exercise
that is now not an anti-movement like
the first two,
but an actual movement one,
and we pick a flexion exercise. Maybe we
do a cable crunch, where I can load it
heavy, I can pull down, and I'm still
going to do my, you know, six to 12
reps.
Not much going on in the spine here.
We're totally safe, but we're able to go
really, really, really heavy. We've done
some of the dynamic movements. We've
done a little bit more of an isolated
exercise, and we've put it all together.
And you could do that
say, 3 days a week.
Or,
you could do that one day a week,
say, day one,
do a different style on day two,
and then come back to this style on day
three.
So, you can mix and match it. What I'm
again, maybe to be a little more clear,
this could be your entire strategy of
how you do your abs for six or eight
weeks.
Or, you could have what we would call an
undulating system where you kind of do
this day one, and then do maybe a higher
repetition strategy
day two or day three of the week. And
now you're doing your sets of 15 or sets
of 30, and you're working on some of the
other stuff that we've talked about in
the past. So, you can mix and match
these into one week, or you could
separate them into multiple months of
training style. Again,
one example. Hopefully, that helped you
kind of conceptualize all the principles
we talked about and what that would
could look like in one program.
I want to before we depart past that
though, talk about this progression cuz
I brought it up multiple times now.
It's very clear. We need to
progressively overload our core muscles
like everything else.
What I personally like to do and this is
again my personal opinion now,
is to use a strategy that is in five
steps. So, step number one, I like to
start with isometric exercise. These are
ab exercises in which you're not moving.
I want to emphasize control here and we
want to develop fatigue resistance.
So, can you hold the proper position?
Number one.
That's what I want to start with. I
don't like loading. I don't like moving
until I know you can actually just get
in the right position and hold it.
This could be your plank exercise.
Can you show me that you can hold it for
60 seconds?
Or 90 seconds or 45 seconds depending on
your age and fitness and stuff.
So, I'm resisting fatigue, which means
I'm getting more confident you're not
going to break down your position
later in the training.
Now, we might stay on these isometric
control exercises for 6 months.
We might stay there for 6 days.
I don't want to progress to step two
though until I'm really really really
confident that your obliques going to
hold the right position.
That your RA can hold the right
position. That your glutes can hold the
right position. That your back and all
of those global core, shoulder girdle,
all of it. Right? We want to be able to
hold the right position first.
Once I'm convinced of that,
I'm cool with going on to step two.
Step two is the anti-movement
kind of eccentric
with fatigue resistance. So, now great,
you can hold a lateral plank
while you're tired. Amazing. Can you
slowly lower
laterally?
To me that's more difficult, right? So,
imagine doing a side bend.
The progression would be uh you know,
again lateral plank and we're good
there. You can hold the lateral plank
for say 60 seconds. I'm good. Now, the
next progression of your exercise would
be to stand up and do a lateral bend.
And we're going to focus on the
eccentric and the the lowering portion.
So, show me you can extend the movement
with a little bit of load and a lot of
repetitions and still continue to move
properly.
If you can do that, then I'm okay with
us adding some load. So, phase three is
still
the either anti-movement or the active
eccentric movement
but with some load. We can get heavy
now.
Lower repetitions, less concerned about
fatigue, and really just can
you actually pushing strength here. Step
four is now the movement side of the
equation. It's the concentric action
with fatigue. So, now can you actively
pull that thing up? Can we do the cable
crunch? Can we can we do more movement
based stuff
for fatigue? And then step five of
course is can we do the movement stuff
with load?
If you can get through all these things,
then I'm very comfortable letting you do
whatever movement pattern we want and
going fast and going heavy and going to
fatigue and I feel like you're going to
be in really good position to do that.
So, that's my personal five-step
progression.
It's isometric control with
failure being induced by fatigue.
Then it is either anti-movement
or direct eccentric movement
where failure comes from fatigue.
Step three is the anti or eccentric
where failure comes from load or heavy.
Step four, concentric
failure fatigue. And then finally step
five is can you move actively
concentrically with a really really
heavy load? A really quick example of
that could look something like this.
So, step number one, that isometric
control and fatigue resistance
is your plank. I gave you examples of a
lateral plank, but for this, you know,
one through five example, we'll just say
a normal plank.
Phase two, the anti-extension
eccentric fatigue
resistance one could look like a reverse
crunch. Still the same movement pattern,
still the same muscle group. It's
reverse crunch. It's a dead bug.
And we're going to do 30 or 40 or 50 or
100 repetitions of it, right? So, now
you're actively letting the rectus
abdominis move eccentrically
under control and you're going to get
tired by doing it.
Step three,
we would progress to say a decline or a
weighted crunch.
So,
again we're doing the eccentric portion,
so you're going to start up maybe with
your
elbows towards your knees and we're
going to work on holding a plate
or a kettlebell or a dumbbell and
lowering it back down to the ground.
Now,
why this becomes a challenge is this
will expose bad technique.
One coaching cue I like a lot here
is when you're doing flexion work, to
move one vertebrae at a time.
This is on the way up and the way down.
I can't I don't know of that much
research here, but I personally have
found
in myself as well as clients
and athletes,
you're far less likely to aggravate back
pain with
flexion based activities when you
literally curl up and curl down one
vertebrae at a time. So, we would work
on that and we would load that
assuming perfect technique. And if
technique
starts to falter,
then we consider that a failure and we
just continue to work on the strength
side of that equation.
The fourth progression here
might be going even further with that
and adding a cable crunch
where we can actively move in the
concentric. So, now imagine, you know,
you're kind of on your hands and knees
and you have a a cable over top of your
head and you're using that to pull the
cable down and pull yourself into the
crunch. So, instead of resisting
you know, lowering the sit-up, you're
adding load where you have to pull the
sit-up with more force and more load. In
this case, we're going to do a lot of
repetitions. This is your classic
sit-up. Fifth and final phase here would
be adding load to that. So, you know,
holding the dumbbell or holding the
cable with added load and doing the
crunchy for really really heavy for five
to eight reps.
Most people,
I'm confident in saying, have never
really tried to go heavy with any of
their ab movements.
And most people that do try it are
stunned with how fast their abs grow in
both strength and particularly in size.
So, at this point, we've actually
covered a lot of ground.
In going through look, feel, and
perform, we talked a lot about exercise
choices.
I kind of buried in there really quickly
frequency,
intensity, volume, and then talked
lastly about progression.
The one variable we have not mentioned
yet is exercise order.
So, we want to think about this as an
issue of priority. Most people do their
core or ab work at the end of their
training session.
I'm fine with that if we understand the
point.
Typically, my rule of thumb,
do the thing that is your highest
priority on that day
first.
So, if you're there with the primary
goal to target your abs for look, feel,
or perform,
then you might consider doing it first.
But I'm fine with you doing it last if
you feel like fatiguing your abs
will take away from another equally or
more important movement.
So, if you're there to work on your abs,
but you also want to really increase
your pull-ups
or your squat or your lunge or anything
else,
you might necessarily
not want to fatigue your abs prior to
that because that'll actually
lower your ability to either execute
that exercise
or increase your injury risk of doing it
cuz you're pre-fatigued.
So, I want to finish by going back to
the beginning. I asked some kind of
silly and bold questions
and I promised we'd come back to it and
here we are.
If we take into consideration things
like
what muscles
or what exercises activate our core
more,
let's see how you do in this little
quiz.
So, we'll go in reverse order. First,
what do we now think about training
frequency?
Do we still think that training every
day is how we have to train our core or
even the best?
Surely not at this point.
I'm okay
with you doing that or in fact I could
argue it is good
if the goal is feel.
If the goal is activation. If the goal
is movement correction.
We need to practice different movement
patterns.
But if we're trying to maximize either
perform
or aesthetics,
we probably actually want to hedge more
towards two to three or four days a week
rather than seven.
So, in reality, it was kind of a trick
question.
Cuz it's correct to do them both ways.
But it's not correct to do them
the wrong way
when we have different goals.
Another thing I brought up were things
like machines
versus unstable surfaces or machines
versus dumbbells and kettlebells.
Are those things in fact more functional
because I have to create more stability?
Maybe.
But not necessarily.
If you were to take a
5-lb dumbbell
and do a 5-lb lateral
side bend
and you compared that to a one
repetition max leg press,
I don't think that studies have been
done, but I'd be willing to bet
your obliques, your rectus abdominis,
and your transverse abdominis are
contracting
far harder
on that leg press than they are that
side bend. If we're equating for load
and other variables, sure. When you have
to stabilize your body
versus when a machine can do it for you,
you should get more activation
from the free weights.
But just because it's a free weight and
just because it's a machine, it does not
guarantee that fact. Execution matters
here more
than exercise choice.
I also brought up things like
a bench press or a deadlift
versus a sit-up.
And where we have to remember here is
while a sit-up in this example might be
more specific
to the muscle in the core,
because I can't load it very heavy
safely for most people,
I'm going to be limited in force demand.
That limitation in force demand is very
similar to what we just got done talking
about. And so in this case,
a bigger, more dynamic exercise might in
fact be more effective for strengthening
or even growing your core muscles.
And the last one I'll give you here,
which is something we didn't get into
too much,
and I'll leave as a teaser,
and that's the entire topic of weight
belts.
You'll hear controversy on this,
but to me, I think the science has been
settled here for over a decade.
If you take a weight belt
and you put it on really tight, you
cinch it all the way down,
you might see
a regression or a drop
in muscle activation during any given
exercise.
But if you put the weight belt on
just barely, kind of snug,
you can actually see increased core
activation because it gives you tactile
feedback.
As the example I gave you earlier when I
said, "Put your hand on your side or put
it on your back or get in this different
position because it causes you some
tactile feedback and you often times
people have a better ability to contract
when they have that feedback. The same
is true of a belt. The evidence as it
currently stands and my personal
approach is to think about belts like
this.
If I need to use it as a way to queue
or to learn an activation strategy,
then I'll put it on there.
But then ideally we progress to the next
step where we can remove it and we have
conscious control
of that musculature or that movement
pattern independent of an external
stimuli.
If we're going to be loading really,
really heavy,
maybe 85% or more of our one rep max
on a bench or a pull-up or an overhead
press or some big movement
and someone feels more secure
and more stable
and they want to add a belt, then I'm
absolutely okay with that because we're
no longer using that movement
to train the core, we're actually trying
to get better at that movement.
And we have plenty of ways to train our
core on separate exercises. So slap on a
belt, even if they want to cinch it down
super tight,
because we're trying to get stronger in
the deadlift or a lunge or something
else.
Totally fine there.
But what we probably want to do is say,
"Okay, whenever we fall, you know, say
below 90% or below 85%, maybe don't use
our belt because we need to make sure
that we're developing enough muscle
strength in that movement to be safe
when we load it heavier."
So hopefully that gives you a little bit
better understanding about how I think
about using belts and how they can both
undercut ab development as well as
accelerate
ab development. It's entirely based upon
not
the technology or the equipment itself,
but how you're utilizing it, when you're
utilizing it, who you're utilizing it
with,
and what the ultimate goal or outcome
is.
Thank you for joining for today's
episode. My goal as always is to share
exciting scientific insights that help
you perform at your best. If the show
resonates with you and you want to help
ensure this information remains free and
accessible to anyone in the world, there
are a few ways that you can support.
First, you can subscribe to the show on
YouTube, Spotify, and Apple. And on
Apple and Spotify, you can leave us up
to a five-star review. Subscribing and
leaving a review really does help us a
lot. Also, please check out our
sponsors. This show would not exist
without them and their exceptional
products and services. Finally, you can
share today's episode with a friend who
you think would enjoy it. If you have
any content questions or suggestions,
please put those in the comments section
on YouTube. I really do try my best to
read them all and to see what you have
to say. I use my Instagram and X
profiles also exclusively for scientific
communication, so those are great places
to follow along for more learning. My
handle is @drandygalpin on both
platforms. We also have an email
newsletter that distills all of our
episodes into the most actionable
takeaways. We have newsletters on how to
improve fitness and VO2 max, how to
build muscle and strength, and much
more. To subscribe to the newsletter,
just go to performpodcast.com
and click newsletter. It's completely
free and we do not share your email with
anybody. Thank you for listening and
never forget in the famous words of Bill
Bowerman, if you have a body, you are an
athlete.